This is my grandfather.
هذا جدي.
And this is my son.
وهذا ابني.
My grandfather taught me to work with wood
علمني جدي العمل بالخشب
when I was a little boy,
عندما كنت ولداً صغيراً،
and he also taught me the idea that
وعلمني أيضاً فكرة أنه
if you cut down a tree to turn it into something,
إذا قطعت شجرة لتحولها إلى شيء ما،
honor that tree's life and make it as beautiful
فاحترم حياة تلك الشجرة واصنع منها شيئاً جميلاً
as you possibly can.
قدر ما تستطيع.
My little boy reminded me
ذكرني ولدي الصغير
that for all the technology and all the toys in the world,
بأن كل التكنولوجيا والألعاب في العالم،
sometimes just a small block of wood,
هي أحياناً مجرد قطعة صغيرة من الخشب،
if you stack it up tall,
إذا كدستها بالطول،
actually is an incredibly inspiring thing.
فإنها تُكون شيئاً ملهماً حقاً.
These are my buildings.
هذه هي مبانيي.
I build all around the world
بنيت حول العالم
out of our office in Vancouver and New York.
خارج مكاتبنا في فانكوفر ونيويورك.
And we build buildings of different sizes and styles
وبنينا مباني بأحجام وتصميمات مختلفة
and different materials, depending on where we are.
وباستخدام مواد مختلفة، اعتماداً على المكان الذي نحن به.
But wood is the material that I love the most,
ولكن الخشب هو المادة التي أحبها أكثر،
and I'm going to tell you the story about wood.
وسأخبركم قصة الخشب.
And part of the reason I love it is that every time
وجزء من السبب في أنني أحبه هو أنه في كل مرة
people go into my buildings that are wood,
يدخل الناس إلى مبانيي الخشبية،
I notice they react completely differently.
ألاحظ أن ردة فعلهم مختلفة بشكل كامل.
I've never seen anybody walk into one of my buildings
لم أرى أبداً أي شخص يدخل أحد مبانيي
and hug a steel or a concrete column,
ويحتضن عمود من الصلب أو الإسمنت،
but I've actually seen that happen in a wood building.
ولكني في الحقيقة رأيت ذلك يحدث في مبنى خشبي.
I've actually seen how people touch the wood,
رأيت فعلاً كيف يلمس الناس الخشب،
and I think there's a reason for it.
وأعتقد أن هناك سبب لذلك.
Just like snowflakes, no two pieces of wood
ومثل ندفات الثلج، لا يوجد قطعتين من الخشب
can ever be the same anywhere on Earth.
متشابهتين أبداً على الأرض.
That's a wonderful thing.
وهذا أمرٌ رائع.
I like to think that wood
أحب أن أفكر بأن الخشب
gives Mother Nature fingerprints in our buildings.
يعطي بصمات للطبيعة الأم في مبانينا.
It's Mother Nature's fingerprints that make
إنها بصمات الطبيعة الأم التي تجعل
our buildings connect us to nature in the built environment.
مبانينا تربطنا بالطبيعة في بيئة البناء.
Now, I live in Vancouver, near a forest
أعيش الآن في فانكوفر، قريباً من غابة
that grows to 33 stories tall.
تنمو بارتفاع 33 طابقاً.
Down the coast here in California, the redwood forest
وهنا على الساحل في كاليفورنيا، غابة الخشب الأحمر
grows to 40 stories tall.
تنمو بارتفاع 40 طابقاً.
But the buildings that we think about in wood
ولكن المباني الخشبية التي نفكر بها
are only four stories tall in most places on Earth.
هي فقط بارتفاع أربعة طوابق في معظم الأماكن على الأرض.
Even building codes actually limit the ability for us to build
حتى قوانين البناء تحد في الحقيقة من قدرتنا على البناء
much taller than four stories in many places,
أعلى من أربعة طوابق في العديد من الأماكن
and that's true here in the United States.
وذلك ينطبق هنا في الولايات المتحدة.
Now there are exceptions,
والآن هناك استثناءات،
but there needs to be some exceptions,
ولكن هناك حاجة إلى أن يكون هناك بعض الاستثناءات،
and things are going to change, I'm hoping.
والأمور سوف تتغير، أتمنى ذلك.
And the reason I think that way is that
والسبب الذي يجعلني أفكر بهذه الطريقة أنه
today half of us live in cities,
نصفنا اليوم يعيش في المدن،
and that number is going to grow to 75 percent.
وذلك الرقم سيزيد إلى 75 في المئة.
Cities and density mean that our buildings
المدن والكثافة السكانية تعني أن مبانينا
are going to continue to be big,
سوف تبقى كبيرة،
and I think there's a role for wood to play in cities.
وأعتقد أن هناك دور للخشب في المدن.
And I feel that way because three billion people
وأشعر بهذا لأن ثلاثة مليارات من الناس
in the world today, over the next 20 years,
في العالم اليوم، وخلال العشرين سنة القادمة،
will need a new home.
سوف يحتاجون إلى بيت جديد.
That's 40 percent of the world that are going to need
وذلك يعني أن 40 في المئة من العالم سوف يحتاجون إلى
Now, one in three people living in cities today
واحد من كل ثلاثة أشخاص اليوم يعيشون في المدن
actually live in a slum.
وفي الواقع يعيشون في أحياء فقيرة.
That's one billion people in the world live in slums.
وذلك يعني أن واحد مليار شخص في العالم يعيشون في أحياء فقيرة.
A hundred million people in the world are homeless.
مئة مليون شخص في العالم هم بلا مأوى.
The scale of the challenge for architects
حجم التحدي للمهندسين المعماريين
and for society to deal with in building
وللمجتمع مع البناء
is to find a solution to house these people.
هو إيجاد حلاً لإيواء هؤلاء الناس.
But the challenge is, as we move to cities,
ولكن التحدي هو، بينما ننتقل للمدن،
cities are built in these two materials,
تُبنى المدن بمادتين،
steel and concrete, and they're great materials.
الصلب والاسمنت، وهما مادتان رائعتان.
They're the materials of the last century.
هما مواد القرن الماضي.
But they're also materials with very high energy
ولكنهما أيضاً مادتين لهما طاقة عالية
and very high greenhouse gas emissions in their process.
وتنتج نسبة كبيرة من الانبعاثات الغازية الدفيئة.
Steel represents about three percent
الصلب يُشكل تقريباً ثلاثة بالمئة
of man's greenhouse gas emissions,
من الانبعاثات الغازية الدفيئة المتسبب فيها الانسان،
and concrete is over five percent.
والاسمنت أكثر من خمسة بالمئة.
So if you think about that, eight percent
لذا إذا فكرت في هذا الأمر، فإن ثمانية بالمئة
of our contribution to greenhouse gases today
من الغازات الدفيئة التي أسهمنا في إنتاجها اليوم
comes from those two materials alone.
تنتج من هاتين المادتين فقط.
We don't think about it a lot, and unfortunately,
نحن لا نفكر في ذلك كثيراً، وللأسف،
we actually don't even think about buildings, I think,
وفي الحقيقة نحن لا نفكر حتى في المباني
as much as we should.
كما يجب.
This is a U.S. statistic about the impact of greenhouse gases.
وهذه إحصائية أمريكية عن تأثير الغازات الدفيئة.
Almost half of our greenhouse gases are related to the building industry,
تقريباً نصف الغازات الدفيئة مرتبطة بصناعة البناء،
and if we look at energy, it's the same story.
وإذا نظرنا للطاقة، فإنها نفس القصة.
You'll notice that transportation's sort of second down that list,
ستلاحظ أن النقل وهو نوعاً ما يأتي في المرتبة الثانية لتلك القائمة،
but that's the conversation we mostly hear about.
إلا أنه ذلك الحديث الذي نسمع عنه دائماً.
And although a lot of that is about energy,
وبالرغم من أن معظم ذلك هو عن الطاقة،
it's also so much about carbon.
إلا أنه أكثر عن الكربون.
The problem I see is that, ultimately,
المشكلة التي أراها هي في النهاية
the clash of how we solve that problem
الاختلاف في كيفية حلنا لمشكلة
of serving those three billion people that need a home,
خدمة أولئك الثلاثة مليارات من الأشخاص الذين يحتاجون مأوى،
and climate change, are a head-on collision
وتغير المناخ، هو تصادم مباشر
about to happen, or already happening.
على وشك الحدوث، أو يحدث بالفعل.
That challenge means that we have to start thinking in new ways,
التحدي يعني أن نبدأ التفكير بطرق جديدة،
and I think wood is going to be part of that solution,
وأعتقد أن الخشب سوف يكون جزء من ذلك الحل،
and I'm going to tell you the story of why.
وسأخبركم قصة اعتقادي هذا.
As an architect, wood is the only material,
الخشب هو المادة الوحيدة،
big material, that I can build with
وهو مادة كبيرة، أستطيع كمهندس معماري البناء بها
that's already grown by the power of the sun.
وهي مادة نمت بقوة الشمس.
When a tree grows in the forest and gives off oxygen
عندما تنمو شجرة في الغابة وتعطي الأكسجين
and soaks up carbon dioxide,
وتمتص ثاني أكسيد الكربون،
and it dies and it falls to the forest floor,
وتموت وتسقط على أرض الغابة،
it gives that carbon dioxide back to the atmosphere or into the ground.
تُخرج ثاني أكسيد الكربون في الجو أو الأرض.
If it burns in a forest fire, it's going to give that carbon
لو احترقت في حريق غابة، سوف تُخرج ذلك الكربون
back to the atmosphere as well.
في الجو أيضاً.
But if you take that wood and you put it into a building
ولكن لو أخذت ذلك الخشب ووضعته في بناء
or into a piece of furniture or into that wooden toy,
أو في قطعة أثاث أو في لعبة خشبية،
it actually has an amazing capacity
فهو في الحقيقة له قدرة تحمل
to store the carbon and provide us with a sequestration.
لخزن الكربون وحبسه عنا.
One cubic meter of wood will store
يُخزن واحد متر مكعب من الخشب
one tonne of carbon dioxide.
واحد طن من ثاني أكسيد الكربون.
Now our two solutions to climate are obviously
الحلان المتوفران لدينا الآن للبيئة هما بشكل واضح
to reduce our emissions and find storage.
تقليل الانبعاثات وإيجاد مخزن.
Wood is the only major material building material
الخشب هو مادة البناء الوحيدة المهمة
I can build with that actually does both those two things.
أستطيع البناء به وهو بالفعل يقدم كلا الحلين.
So I believe that we have
لذا أعتقد أن لدينا
an ethic that the Earth grows our food,
مبدأ أخلاقي وهو أن الأرض تنتج طعامنا،
and we need to move to an ethic in this century
ونحتاج أن ننتقل إلى مبدأ أخلاقي آخر في هذا القرن
that the Earth should grow our homes.
وهو أن الأرض يجب أن تُنتج بيوتنا.
Now, how are we going to do that
والآن كيف نقوم بعمل ذلك
when we're urbanizing at this rate
ونحن نتمدن بهذا المعدل
and we think about wood buildings only at four stories?
ونحن نفكر في المباني الخشبية بأربعة طوابق فقط؟
We need to reduce the concrete and steel and we need
نحتاج أن نقلل حاجتنا إلى الأسمنت والصلب ونحتاج
to grow bigger, and what we've been working on
أن نبني مباني أطول، ونحن نعمل على بناء
is 30-story tall buildings made of wood.
مباني خشبية من 30 طابق.
We've been engineering them with an engineer
صممها مهندس
named Eric Karsh who works with me on it,
يسمى إيريك كارش وهو يعمل معي في هذا،
and we've been doing this new work because
ونقوم بهذا العمل الجديد لأنه
there are new wood products out there for us to use,
هناك منتجات خشبية جديدة متوفرة لنا لنستخدمها
and we call them mass timber panels.
ونسميها ألواح خشبية متكتلة.
These are panels made with young trees,
هذه الألواح مصنوعة من شجر صغير،
small growth trees, small pieces of wood
وشجيرات صغيرة، وقطع صغيرة من الخشب
glued together to make panels that are enormous:
تلصق معاً لصنع الألواح والتي تكون ضخمة:
eight feet wide, 64 feet long, and of various thicknesses.
عرضها ثمانية أقدام وطولها 64 قدم وبكثافات مختلفة.
The way I describe this best, I've found, is to say
وجدت أن أفضل طريقة لشرح هذا هو
that we're all used to two-by-four construction
أننا جميعاً معتادين على مبنى اثنين في أربعة
when we think about wood.
عندما نتحدث عن الخشب.
That's what people jump to as a conclusion.
ذلك ما يستنتجه الناس مباشرة.
Two-by-four construction is sort of like the little
مبنى اثنين في أربعة هو نوعاً ما مثل
eight-dot bricks of Lego that we all played with as kids,
طوبة ذات الثمانية نقاط من لعبة الليغو التي لعبناها جميعاً عندما كنا أطفالاً
and you can make all kinds of cool things out of Lego
وتستطيع أن تبني أشياء رائعة من لعبة الليغو
at that size, and out of two-by-fours.
بذلك الحجم وبحجم اثنين في أربعة.
But do remember when you were a kid,
ولكن تذكر عندما كنت طفلاً،
and you kind of sifted through the pile in your basement,
أنت تبحث في كومة الطوبات في الطابق تحت الأرضي،
and you were kind of like,
وكأنك عندها تقول،
"Cool, this is awesome. I can build something really big,
"رائع، هذ مدهش. أستطيع أن أبني شيئاً كبيراً بالفعل،
and this is going to be great."
وسيكون عظيماً."
That's the change.
هذا هو التغيير.
Mass timber panels are those 24-dot bricks.
الألواح الخشبية المتكتلة هي الطوبات ذات 24 نقطة.
They're changing the scale of what we can do,
إنهم يغيرون مستوى الأشياء التي يمكننا عملها،
and what we've developed is something we call FFTT,
والذي طورناه هو شيء نسميه إف إف تي تي،
which is a Creative Commons solution
وهو حل منظمة المشاع الابداعي
to building a very flexible system
لبناء نظام مرن جداً
of building with these large panels where we tilt up
للبناء باستخدام تللك الالواح الكبيرة حيث نغطي
six stories at a time if we want to.
ستة طوابق في وقت واحد إذا أردنا.
This animation shows you how the building goes together
هذا التصوير الحركي يُظهر لكم المباني معاً
in a very simple way, but these buildings are available
بطريقة بسيطة، ولكن هذه المباني متوفرة الآن
for architects and engineers now to build on
للمهندسين المعماريين والمصممين ليعتمدوها في البناء،
for different cultures in the world,
لثقافات مختلفة في العالم،
different architectural styles and characters.
على تصاميم هندسية معمارية وأشكال مختلفة.
In order for us to build safely,
من أجل أن نبني بأمان،
we've engineered these buildings, actually,
صممنا في الحقيقة هذه المباني
to work in a Vancouver context,
لنعمل في مدينة كفانكوفر،
where we're a high seismic zone,
حيث أننا في منطقة عالية الزلزالية،
even at 30 stories tall.
وصولاً إلى 30 طابق ارتفاعاً.
Now obviously, every time I bring this up,
من الواضح الآن أنه في كل مرة أذكر فيها هذا الأمر
people even, you know, here at the conference, say,
يقول الناس حتى هنا في المؤتمر،
"Are you serious? Thirty stories? How's that going to happen?"
"هل أنت جاد؟ ثلاثون طابقاً؟ كيف سيتم ذلك؟
And there's a lot of really good questions that are asked
وهناك الكثير من الأسئلة الجيدة التي سُئلت
and important questions that we spent quite a long time
والكثيرة من الأسئلة المهمة التي قضينا وقت طويل جداً
working on the answers to as we put together
نعمل على إيجاد إجابات لها بينما نحن نضع معاً
our report and the peer reviewed report.
تقريرنا والتقرير التقييمي للمختصين.
I'm just going to focus on a few of them,
سوف أركز فقط على بعضها،
and let's start with fire, because I think fire
ولنبدأ بالحريق، لأنني أعتقد أن الحريق
is probably the first one that you're all thinking about right now.
والذي من المحتمل أن يكون أول شيء تفكرون به الآن.
And the way I describe it is this.
والطريقة التي أصف بها الأمر كالتالي:
If I asked you to take a match and light it
لو طلبت منك أخذ عود كبريت وإشعاله
and hold up a log and try to get that log to go on fire,
وأن تمسك بقطعة من الحطب وتحاول إشعال تلك القطعة،
it doesn't happen, right? We all know that.
هذا لن يحدث، أليس كذلك؟ نحن جميعاً نعلم ذلك.
But to build a fire, you kind of start with small pieces
ولكن أن تُشعل ناراً، فأنت نوعاً ما تبدأ بقطع صغيرة
of wood and you work your way up,
من الخشب وتُشعلها
and eventually you can add the log to the fire,
وأخيراً يمكنك أن تضيف قطعة الحطب للنار
and when you do add the log to the fire, of course,
وعندما تضيف قطعة الحطب للنار فإنها بالطبع
it burns, but it burns slowly.
ستشتعل ولكن ستشتعل ببطء.
Well, mass timber panels, these new products
حسناً، الألواح الخشبية المتكتلة، هذه المنتجات الجديدة
that we're using, are much like the log.
التي نستخدمها، هي تشبه قطعة الحطب.
It's hard to start them on fire, and when they do,
من الصعب أن تشعلها، وعندما تفعل ذلك،
they actually burn extraordinarily predictably,
هي في الحقيقة تحترق بصورة ملحوظة ومتوقعة،
and we can use fire science in order to predict
ويمكننا أن نستخدم علم الحريق من أجل أن نتوقع
and make these buildings as safe as concrete
وأن نجعل هذه المباني آمنة تماماً كالإسمنت
and as safe as steel.
وآمنة تماماً كالصلب.
The next big issue, deforestation.
والمسألة الكبيرة التالية هي التصحر.
Eighteen percent of our contribution
ثمانية عشر بالمئة من إسهامنا
to greenhouse gas emissions worldwide
في الانبعاثات الغازية الدفيئة في العالم
is the result of deforestation.
هو نتيجة للتصحر.
The last thing we want to do is cut down trees.
آخر شيء نرغب بفعله هو قطع الأشجار.
Or, the last thing we want to do is cut down the wrong trees.
أو آخر شيء نرغب بفعله هو قطع الأشجار بشكل خاطئ.
There are models for sustainable forestry
هناك نماذج للحراجة المحتملة
that allow us to cut trees properly,
التي تسمح لنا بقص الأشجار بطرية مناسبة،
and those are the only trees appropriate
وتلك هي فقط الأشجار المناسبة
to use for these kinds of systems.
للاستخدام لهذا النوع من الأنظمة.
Now I actually think that these ideas
وأنا الآن بالفعل أعتقد أن هذه الأفكار
will change the economics of deforestation.
سوف تغير علم اقتصاد التصحر.
In countries with deforestation issues,
في الدول التي بها مشاكل تصحر،
we need to find a way to provide
نحتاج أن نجد طريقة لنقدم
better value for the forest
قيمة أفضل للغابة
and actually encourage people to make money
ونشجع الناس لكسب المال
through very fast growth cycles --
من خلال دورات النمو السريعة جداً--
10-, 12-, 15-year-old trees that make these products
الشجر ذو 10-، 12-، 15- سنة الذي يصنع هذه المنتجات
and allow us to build at this scale.
ويسمح لنا بالبناء على هذا المستوى.
We've calculated a 20-story building:
حسبنا مبنى من 20 طابق:
We'll grow enough wood in North America every 13 minutes.
سننتج خشب كافي في أمريكا الشمالية كل 13 دقيقة.
That's how much it takes.
ذلك كل ما يحتاج إليه الأمر.
The carbon story here is a really good one.
قصة الكربون هنا هي قصة جيدة حقاً.
If we built a 20-story building out of cement and concrete,
لو بنينا مبنى من عشرين طابق من الاسمنت والصلب،
the process would result in the manufacturing
ستُنتج عملية التصنيع
of that cement and 1,200 tonnes of carbon dioxide.
من ذلك الاسمنت 1200 طن من ثاني أكسيد الكربون.
If we did it in wood, in this solution,
لو بنيناه بالخشب، فبهذا الحل،
we'd sequester about 3,100 tonnes,
سنحبس 3100 طن
for a net difference of 4,300 tonnes.
لصافي الفرق 4300 طن.
That's the equivalent of about 900 cars
هذا مساوي تقريباً ل900 سيارة
removed from the road in one year.
أُزيلت من الطريق في سنة واحدة.
Think back to that three billion people
فكروا مرة أخرى بالثلاثة مليار شخص
that need a new home,
الذين يحتاجون بيوت جديدة،
and maybe this is a contributor to reducing.
وربما يكون هذا مساهم في التقليل.
We're at the beginning of a revolution, I hope,
نحن في بداية ثورة
in the way we build, because this is the first new way
في طريقة البناء، كما آمل، لأن هذه هي الطريقة الأولى والجديدة
But the challenge is changing society's perception
ولكن التحدي هو تغيير إدراك المجتمع
of possibility, and it's a huge challenge.
للإمكانيات، وهذا تحدي كبير.
The engineering is, truthfully, the easy part of this.
فالهندسة هي حقيقة الجزء السهل في هذا الأمر.
And the way I describe it is this.
والطريقة التي أصف بها الأمر هي كالتالي:
The first skyscraper, technically --
ناطحة السحاب الأولى، عملياً--
and the definition of a skyscraper is 10 stories tall, believe it or not —
وتعريف ناطحة السحاب هي أنها عشرة طوابق ارتفاعاً، صدق أو لا تصدق-
but the first skyscraper was this one in Chicago,
ولكن ناطحة السحاب الأولى هي هذه في شيكاغو،
and people were terrified to walk underneath this building.
وكان الناس خائفون من المشي تحت المبنى.
But only four years after it was built,
ولكن بعد بناءها بأربع سنوات،
Gustave Eiffel was building the Eiffel Tower,
كان جوستاف ايفل يبني برج ايفل،
and as he built the Eiffel Tower,
وبينما كان يبني برج ايفل،
he changed the skylines of the cities of the world,
غير آفاق مدن العالم،
changed and created a competition
غير وخلق منافسة
between places like New York City and Chicago,
بين الأماكن مثل مدينة نيويورك وشيكاغو،
where developers started building bigger and bigger buildings
حيث بدأ المطورون بناء مباني أكبر وأكبر
and pushing the envelope up higher and higher
ودفع الغطاء أعلى وأعلى
with better and better engineering.
بهندسة أفضل وأفضل.
We built this model in New York, actually,
بنينا هذا النموذج في نيويورك
as a theoretical model on the campus
في الحقيقة كنموذج نظري في حرم
of a technical university soon to come,
جامعة تقنية حديثة،
and the reason we picked this site
والسبب في اختيار هذا الموقع
to just show you what these buildings may look like,
هو فقط لإطلاعكم على كيف تبدو هذه المباني،
because the exterior can change.
لأن المظهر الخارجي يمكن أن يتغير.
It's really just the structure that we're talking about.
إنه فقط البناء ما نتحدث عنه في الواقع.
The reason we picked it is because this is a technical university,
السبب في اختيارنا للموقع هو أنه جامعة تقنية،
technologically advanced material I can build with.
المادة الأكثر تقدماً تكنولوجياً وأستطيع البناء بها.
It just happens to be that Mother Nature holds the patent,
وقد صادف أن الطبيعة الأم تملك براءة الاختراع ،
and we don't really feel comfortable with it.
ونحن حقاً لا نشعر بالراحة لذلك.
But that's the way it should be,
ولكن هذا ما يجب أن يكون عليه الأمر،
nature's fingerprints in the built environment.
بصمات الطبيعة في بيئة البناء.
I'm looking for this opportunity
أنا أنظر لهذه الفرصة
to create an Eiffel Tower moment, we call it.
لخلق لحظة برج ايفل كما نسميها.
Buildings are starting to go up around the world.
المباني بدأت ترتفع حول العالم.
There's a building in London that's nine stories,
هناك مبنى في لندن وهو يتكون من تسعة طوابق،
a new building that just finished in Australia
مبنى جديد في استراليا
that I believe is 10 or 11.
والذي أعتقد أنه يتكون من 10 أو 11 طابق.
We're starting to push the height up of these wood buildings,
بدأنا نزيد ارتفاع هذه المباني الخشبية،
and we're hoping, and I'm hoping,
ونحن نأمل، وأنا آمل،
that my hometown of Vancouver actually potentially
أن مدينتي فانكوفر، وهي في الحقيقة يحتمل، أن
announces the world's tallest at around 20 stories
تعلن عن أعلى مبنى في العالم من 20 طابق
in the not-so-distant future.
في المستقبل القريب.
That Eiffel Tower moment will break the ceiling,
لحظة برج ايفل ستكسر السقف،
these arbitrary ceilings of height,
هذه الأسقف المرتفعة اعتباطاً،
and allow wood buildings to join the competition.
وتسمح للمباني الخشبية بأن تنضم للمنافسة.
And I believe the race is ultimately on.
وأعتقد أن السباق أخيراً قد بدأ.
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)